Guide to the James Merrill Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- October 2007 Acquisition, 1944-2006; 4; 5; (9 boxes) + 1 art
  - Collected Poems of James Merrill, corrected proof, 7 (Box 42)
  - Collected Poems of James Merrill, proof (photocopy), 7 (Box 42)
  - Collected Poems of James Merrill, dust jacket proof
  - Unsorted materials (Box 42)
  - Collected Poems of James Merrill, proof, 3 (Box 42)
  - Collected Poems of James Merrill, proof, 3 (Box 43)
  - Collected Pomes of James Merrill, galley proof corrected by Patrick Merla, 2 (Box 43)
  - Collected Poems of James Merrill, production material, circa 2000 (Box 43)
  - Collected Prose of James Merrill, proofs, 7 (Box 43)
  - Collected Prose of James Merrill, production material, circa 2007 (Box 43)
  - Final Versions. A Digital Archive of Revisions for Scholars & Students, (1 computer disk)
    Computer disk is restricted. Copies of electronic files may be resquested through Access Services: Disk #20071030-11173.0001
  - Photographs, 3 (Box 43)
  - Letter by Arnold Zweig dated 1944, purchased by J. D. McClatchy on E-Bay (Box 43)
  - Tape from James Merrill's answering machine (Box 43)
  - Souvenir leaf (framed) (Box 43)
  - J. D. McClatchy's diary on the illness of James Merrill (including taped-in medical papers, correspondence, and other documents), 1993-1994 (Box 43)
  - The Wylie Agency, Royalty statements, 2006 (Box 43)
  - Printed material relating to James Merrill (Box 44)
  - Correspondence (Box 44)
  - Small press ephemera (Box 44)
  - "Phaedra: an opera in two acts, performed by The Little Players" and Maya Deren, "Voices of Haiti", compact discs (Box 44)
  - Printed publications, 1980, 2001 (Box 44)
  - Slides, From travels outside USA (Box 45)
  - Slides, From travels outside USA (Box 46)
  - Slides, From travels outside USA (Box 47)
  - Oversize
    - Collected Poems of James Merrill, dust jacket proof (Box 48 (Oversize))
  - Restricted Fragile
    - Computer disks (Box 49)
      Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Object
    - Travelling Case which formerly held slides and photographs (Box 50 (Art))
- October 2009 Acquisition, 1946-2009; 5; 1.75; (4 boxes)
  Gift of J. D. McClatchy, 2009.
  Box 54 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  This portion of the collection consists of correspondence, typescripts, proofs and printed material relating to James Merrill selected poems, edited by J. D. McClatchy and Stephen Yenser, with other related papers.
  Formerly classed as: Uncat MSS 1222
  - Correspondence, 2007-2009; 3 (Box 51)
  - James Merrill April 1 1987 Poetry Center University of Tucson, 1987 April 1; (4 computer disks)
    Computer disks are restricted. Copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services:
    Disk #20091005-33010.0002
    Disk #20091005-33010.0003
    Disk #20091005-33010.0004
    Disk #20091005-33010.0005
  - Key West Literary Seminar, 1993; (1 computer disk)
    Computer disk is restricted. Copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services:
    Disk #20091005-33010.0001
  - James Merrill Selected Poems
    - Book jacket, 2008 (Box 51)
    - Notes, undated (Box 51)
    - Typescript (partial), undated (Box 51)
    - Proof, 2008 (Box 51)
    - Uncorrected proof, 2008 (Box 51)
    - 2nd pass proof, 2008; 3 (Box 51)
    - Review, 2008 (Box 52)
  - Printed material, 1993-2009 (Box 52)
  - Royalty statements, 2008-2009 (Box 52)
  - Merrill/Cavafy project reject sheets, 2008 (Box 52)
  - Phaedra: an Opera in Two Acts, compact disc, undated (Box 52)
  - Printed material, 1946, undated (Box 52)
  - Three silver nesting cups in leather case, undated (Box 53)
- December 2010 Acquisition, 1946-2010; 6; 0.5; (2 boxes)
  Gift of J. D. McClatchy, 2010.
  This portion of the collection consists of material pertaining to James Merrill, created and accumulated by J. D. McClatchy who was executor of Merrill's estate, including the original collage by Debra Greger used as the cover for Recitative by James Merrill.
  Formerly classed as: Uncat MSS 1260
  - Hammer, Langdon. James Merrill: Life and Art, drafts and correspondence, circa 2010; 3 (Box 55)
  - Correspondence relating to publications, 2010 (Box 55)
  - Postcards and miscellaneous publications, 2010 (Box 55)
  - Poetry in Person, uncorrected proof, 2010 (Box 55)
  - "History of the Class of 1943, The Lawrenceville School, 1943-1958", circa 1958 (Box 55)
  - School papers, post card, and flight ticket, circa 1946 (Box 55)
  - Greger, Debra. Original collage used for cover of JM's Recitative, undated (Box 55)
  - "Charioteer," poem and music, undated (Box 56 (Oversize))
- October 2013 Acquisition, circa 1946-2013; 7; 3.17; (3 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 2011-2013 (Box 57)
    Mail and printed email correspondence.
  - Correspondence, 2008-2013 (Box 57)
  - Correspondence, 2011; 2 folders (Box 57)
    Printed email correspondence.
  - List of books from David Jackson's apartment, 2012 (Box 57)
  - Printed materials, 2009-2013; 2 folders (Box 57)
    Internet printouts and printed materials about Merrill, J.D. McClatchy, and Doris Jackson.
  - Royalty statements, 2010-2012 (Box 57)
  - Secret box, undated (Box 57)
    Box for secretly storing valuables made from a book.
  - Drafts by Langdon Hammer, "James Merrill: Life and Art", circa 2014; 3 folders (Box 57)
    Includes the chapters "The Broken Home" and "Costumes and Masks."
  - Notes and index for Merrill's Collected Prose, 2004-07 (Box 57)
  - "The Changing Light at Sandover" proof and other materials, 1972-2011; 5 folders (Box 57)
  - Printed materials, 1946-1990; 6 folders (Box 58)
    Books, reference books, and pamphlets with inscriptions and margin notes.
  - Publication related materials, 1986-2013 (Box 58)
    Correspondence, printed program, and publisher ephemera.
  - James Merrill House t-shirt., undated (Box 58)
  - Music for "Days of 1994," other printed materials., 1994, 2013 (Box 59)
  - Printed materials (Box A)
- November 2015 Acquisition, 1994-2015; 8; 1.88; (5 boxes)
  - Correspondence, printed materials, and royalty statements, 1994-2015; 2 folders (Box 60)
    Correspondence includes postal, email and greeting cards. Printed materials include clippings, magazines, news papers and journals.
  - Correspondence and printed materials, 2014-2015 (Box 60)
    Correspondence includes email, postal and others. Printed materials includes, clippings, magazines and syposium folder.
  - Newspapers, 2015 (Box 61)
  - Broadside and exhibit catalog with correspondence, 2015 (Box 61)
  - Uncorrected proof of "James Merril Life and Art", by Langdon Hammer, 2015; 2 folders (Box 62)
  - Audiovisual material, circa 1995; 2
    Recordings of Merrill's memorial service.
    - Merrill memorial, 1995; 1 (Box 63)
    - Merrill memorial, New York Public Library, May 13, 1995, 1995 May 13; 1 (Box 63)
  - Electronic media, circa 2000
    - Voices of Haiti, recorded by Maya Deren, circa 2000; 1 (Box 64)
    - Phaedra, performed by The Little Players, circa 2000; 1 (Box 64)
    - Songs, by Daron Hagen, circa 2000; 1 (Box 64)
  - Printed materials (Box B)